Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is daf
tet דף ט, daf tet, nine, and we pick up at the
bottom of chet amud bet ח עמוד ב chet amud bet and
we have been discussing after a complicated discussions about mavoys מבואות mavoys
opening up at chatzeros חצרות chatzeros and various types of configurations. We're
now discussing a more straightforward question about can you carry underneath the
beam, under the korah קורה. korah. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara had
opinions both ways and said it really is not dependent on whether
you think the korah קורה korah is because of heker היכר heker
as some type of a signal, as some type of a sign,
or whether it's mechitzah מחיצה, mechitzah, a wall, because either way you
consider it, the question is still, is the wall on the inner
part of the beam or the outer part of the beam? Is
the heker היכר heker for those standing on the inside or the
heker היכר heker for those on the outside? So that can go
either way. Now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says the following,
four lines from the bottom on chet amud bet ח עמוד ב.
chet amud bet. Amar Rav Chisda אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
says Rav Chisda, whatever your position is about the korah קורה, korah,
the beam, everybody agrees bayn lechayayim בין לחיים bayn lechayayim and base
opposite the lechi לחי. lechi. Now it's in the plural but it
sounds like there's a lechi לחי lechi on either side. The lechi
לחי lechi is the post, but it really only is a lechi
לחי lechi on one side, so it's interesting that he used the
plural. But anyway, everybody agrees that opposite the lechi לחי lechi she'assur
שאסור, she'assur, that it is forbidden. Now it's not exactly clear why
it's forbidden. I mean, a lechi לחי lechi also there's a debate,
is it heker היכר, heker, is it mechitzah מחיצה? mechitzah? And you
could also debate for the inside and for the outside, and does
the wall on the inside or the wall on the outside. So
Tosafos תוספות Tosafos says that the reason his claim is that everybody
agrees the lechi לחי lechi is forbidden is because while a korah
קורה korah has to be a tefach טפח tefach wide, a lechi
לחי lechi can be infinitesimally thin. So it's not always infinitesimally thin,
but since it's allowed to be, that the ruling would be we
won't let you use the space opposite the lechi לחי lechi because
it could be that it's so thin that you'll, you know, that
there won't really be any substantial space there and if we let
you use it, you'll easily step over it. So that's how Tosafos
תוספות Tosafos explains that position. It's interesting that the Gemara גמרא Gemara
does not really offer any explanation why this is that is different
than under the korah קורה. korah. Yes, ok,
so all those are good questions, but we'll have to see when
we get, you know, the Gemara גמרא Gemara hasn't really dealt directly
with a lechi לחי lechi but it is a good question. What
type of a heker היכר heker is it if it's so thin?
Let's see what the Gemara גמרא, Gemara, let's see how the Gemara
גמרא Gemara continues. So bay mineh Rami bar Chama meRav Chisda בעי
מיניה רמי בר חמא מרב חסדא, bay mineh Rami bar Chama meRav
Chisda, so bar Chama asked Rav Chisda. Na'atz shtay yetaydot bishnay kotlay
maboy mibachutz נעץ שתי יתידות בשני כותלי מבוי מבחוץ. na'atz shtay yetaydot
bishnay kotlay maboy mibachutz.
If somebody stuck two pegs on the on the outside of the
maboy מבוי, maboy, meaning you have the open walls at the end
and rather than putting the beam, here are let's take a, okay
here. Anyway,
here's your standard maboy מבוי maboy and here's your standard beam on
top of the maboy מבוי. maboy. But rather than putting it on
top of the walls of the maboy מבוי, maboy, you stuck pegs
out and you put the beam directly flush against the outside face
of the maboy מבוי maboy but not on top of it, but
against the against the face of the maboy מבוי. maboy. Okay, you
got little pegs out and it's suspended and it's flush against the
face of the maboy מבוי. maboy. So what's the story? Na'atz shtay
yetaydot bishnay kotlay maboy mibachutz נעץ שתי יתידות בשני כותלי מבוי מבחוץ.
na'atz shtay yetaydot bishnay kotlay maboy mibachutz. So two two pegs on
the two on the two walls of the maboy מבוי, maboy, the
face of the maboy מבוי maboy on the outside. He'neach korah gabehen
הניח קורה גביהן he'neach korah gabehen and you put the beam on
top of them. Mahu מהו, mahu, what's the story? So amar lay
ledvray hamatir assur uledvray ha'ossur muttar אמר ליה לדברי המתיר אסור ולדברי
האוסר מותר. amar lay ledvray hamatir assur uledvray ha'ossur muttar. Very ingenious,
he said. According to the one who says you're allowed to use
the space under the beam, it's because we go by the outside
part of the beam. Well if you go by the outside part
of the beam, if now the beam is the back of the
beam is flush against the maboy מבוי, maboy, the outside part of
it is distant from the maboy מבוי. maboy. So if you, so
it's not like the, so the part of the beam that actually
validates is not connected to the maboy מבוי, maboy, it's away from
the maboy מבוי maboy because the outside face is now distant. So
the one who says it's muttar מותר muttar underneath would say it's
assur אסור. assur. The one who says it's assur אסור assur underneath
says you go by the inside face of the maboy מבוי. maboy.
That would say it's okay because the inside, I mean the inside
face of the korah קורה korah is flush against the maboy מבוי.
maboy. So it's interesting, although you could say even the outside face,
it's not three tefachim טפחים tefachim away, normally say within three tefachim
טפחים tefachim is lood לבוד, lood, it's like it's flat against, but
here he feels that it has to be directly connected to the
maboy מבוי. maboy. Rava amar רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says, ledvray
ha'ossur nami assur לדברי האוסר נמי אסור. ledvray ha'ossur nami assur. Even
the one that says it's normally it's forbidden under the beam, that
you go by the inside face, here also it'd be forbidden. Why?
At least the inside face of the beam is flush against the
maboy מבוי, maboy, ba'inan korah gabay maboy veleka בעינן קורה גבי מבוי
וליכא. ba'inan korah gabay maboy veleka. We need it, the way Chazzal
חז״ל Chazzal define the beam is that it has to be directly
above. Sort of like by the way, you know that we're going
to say this by tzurat hapetach צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. And it's
interesting, you know the Gemara גמרא Gemara has never explicitly said this,
but it's pretty inescapable that the idea of the korah קורה korah
or the the the lechi לחי lechi or the korah קורה korah
are the constituent parts of a tzurat hapetach צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
of a doorframe. Now you either have, you know, the beams or
you have the lintel. So by tzurat hapetach צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
we know that. And this is why we can't just use telephone
poles straight for צורת הפתח, Tzurat HaPetach, that the top part has
to go directly above the beam. It can't be off to the
side of the beam. Okay? So that's the normal definition of a
צורת הפתח. Tzurat HaPetach. Here too, he's saying if your beam is
flush against the face of the מבוי, mavoi, that's not how we
define the קורה. kora. We define the קורה kora as directly on
top of the walls of the מבוי, mavoi, not flush against the
side of the מבוי. mavoi. Now he doesn't give an explanation, he
just says that's it. You know, again, whether it's however it's functioning,
חז"ל Chazal at a certain point define technical criteria. And here, one
of the technical criteria is flush against the top, not off to
the side. Very much like a צורת הפתח. Tzurat HaPetach. Okay, so
wait, so is this a לחי? lechi? This is the קורה. kora.
You mean the קורה? kora? Right. Do you need a קורה kora
as a צורת הפתח? Tzurat HaPetach? Well, but as I said, one
way about thinking about it is it's a piece of a צורת
הפתח. Tzurat HaPetach. So you don't need a full צורת הפתח, Tzurat
HaPetach, but you need a piece. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't explain
why, just says that's the definition. A קורה kora is on top
of the walls of מבוי, mavoi, not off to the side. איתיבי
רב אדא בר מתנא לרבא. Eiseivei Rav Ada Bar Matna LeRava. רב
אדא בר מתנא Rav Ada Bar Matna asks רבא. Rava. היתה קורתו
משוכה או תלויה. Haita koraso meshucha o tluyah. If your wall, now
I should say by the way, even though you do need it
on the top and not off to the side, you could have
it inside the wall of the מבוי mavoi lower down. When we
learned the first משנה mishna that said if it was too high,
right, what do you do? And we talked about raising the floor,
I told you at that time that the פוסקים poskim also say
you could lower the beam. So it doesn't have to be as
long as it so it's interesting, while it can't be off to
the side, up to the top, it doesn't have to be literally
on top. But anyway, okay, now we're going to challenge this idea
that it has to be on top and cannot be off to
the side. היתה קורתו, Haita koraso, we have a ברייתא. braita. If
your קורה kora was משוכה, meshucha, was extended, או תלויה, o tluyah,
or suspended. Now what does it mean extended or suspended? We assume
what it means is extended means it's not it's not directly on
top but it's off away from the מבוי, mavoi, from it's off
like facing out against the face of the מבוי, mavoi, not on
top of the מבוי. mavoi. So it's drawn away from the מבוי.
mavoi. תלויה, Tluyah, suspended means that it is not extending to the
sides of the walls. Okay? So if this if this is it,
it's suspended somehow, you know, by a post in the middle, but
it doesn't actually reach the edge of the walls. Is that as
clear? All right, so it's either one. רש"י Rashi has a sort
of a picture. So משוכה, meshucha, and let me draw a picture
before we can just get rid of this, by the way, this
picture was so complicated, that was with us for like two days.
Okay? But anyway,
so if
here are the walls of your מבוי, mavoi,
okay, so that's your walls of מבוי. mavoi. So your standard one
is here on top. So משוכה meshucha is so משוכה meshucha is
that you've got pegs and it's extended it's not it's away it's
not on top but it's sort of like that and תלויה tluyah
would be a case where if these are if this is the
edge of your מבוי, mavoi, that it's goes doesn't reach to the
edge. It has something holding it up and it doesn't actually it
has this space here that doesn't reach to the end. Okay? So
when it's משוכה meshucha or
תלויה, tluyah, פחות מג', pachos migimmel, if it's within three טפחים, tfachim,
the standard three טפחים tfachim is לבוד, lavud, it considered something to
be connected. אין צריך להביא קורה אחרת, ein tzarich lehavi kora acheres,
you don't need another beam. You can use this. ג', gimmel, if
it's within three, three or more, excuse me, צריך להביא קורה אחרת,
tzarich lehavi kora acheres, you need another one. And רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel interestingly, we always assume three is לבוד,
lavud, you know, הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe miSinai, the גמרא Gemara
said before that שיעורים shiurim are הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe miSinai,
מחיצות mechitzos are הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe miSinai, and one of
those is the idea that לבוד, lavud, things are considered connected within
three. Nevertheless, comes along רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel
and says it's not three טפחים, tfachim, it's four טפחים. tfachim. פחות
מד' אין צריך להביא קורה אחרת. pachos midaled ein tzarich lehavi kora
acheres. If it's less than four you don't need another קורה, kora,
it's considered connected. ד', daled, of it's four or more, צריך להביא
קורה אחרת, tzarich lehavi kora acheres, you need another beam. So Charlie's
going to ask according to the רמב"ם Rambam there's never debates about
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe miSinai. That's just why which is why
I made that point. Okay? So that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says.
There's a lot of גמרות gemaros that contradict the רמב"ם. Rambam. All
right, anyway, מאי לאו, mai lav, so you see that we're saying
if it's if it's drawn away. משוכה, meshucha, drawn away means מבחוץ,
mibachutz, even if it's drawn away from the מבוי, mavoi, it's on
it's face it's on the face of the מבוי mavoi or even
a little distance from the face of the מבוי, mavoi, not directly
over, but it's away from the front wall of the מבוי. mavoi.
And even so it could be כשר kosher if it's within three
טפחים. tfachim. And you're telling me that it's not כשר, kosher, it
has to be directly on top. So ותלויה vtluya and suspended means
מבפנים, mibifnim, that is within the walls of the מבוי mavoi but
it's drawn away from each side. It's suspended and therefore not touching
the side. So the גמרא Gemara says so you see that contradiction,
it says that even if it's drawn away from the face of
the מבוי mavoi it could still be כשר. kosher. The גמרא Gemara
says לא, lo, no, that's not what it means. אידי ואידי מבפנים,
idi v'idi mibifnim, in both scenarios is it within the walls of
the מבוי. mavoi. So what's the two cases? So what's the two
cases? What does משוכה meshucha mean versus תלויה? tluyah? משוכה מרוח אחת
meshucha mi-ruach achat ותלויה משתי רוחות. ve-tluyah mi-shtei ruchot. It's really describing
more or less the same scenario. משוכה meshucha means it's separated from
one wall, it doesn't extend all the way over to the other
wall, and תלויה tluyah means it's suspended in the middle, it's drawn
away from both walls. Okay? So that's what it means. And מהו
דתימא, mahu de-teima, now why do you have to tell me both
cases? Because I would have thought
דרוח אחת אמרינן לבוד, de-ruach achat amrinan lavud, that from on one
end you can say לבוד. lavud. If it doesn't reach one wall,
if it's within three טפחים tefachim you could say okay, it's flush,
it's like it's connected to that wall. But משתי רוחות לא אמרינן
לבוד, mi-shtei ruchot lo amrinan lavud, you wouldn't say it in two
directions? Maybe you only get to do this once, not twice? קא
משמע לן kamashma lan that you can even you can even do
it on both edge on both sides of the beam. And if
it's removed not touching the wall on either side, you're still okay.
Okay. That's one answer. But it does not mean it's removed from,
you know, the walls of the, meaning it's removed from front of
the מבוי. mavoi. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav
Ashi has another explanation of what משוכה meshucha and תלויה tluyah mean
but still to reconcile it with what we said that it has
to be within the walls of the מבוי. mavoi. משוכה והיא תלויה.
meshucha ve-hi tluyah. It is both it is both drawn away and
suspended above. So what does that mean? He says
כגון שנעץ שתי יתידות עקומות על שתי כותלי מבוי שאין בגובהן ג'
ואין בעקמימותן ג'. kegon she-natze shtei yetedot akumot al shtei kotlei mavoi
she-ein begovah gimel ve-ein beakmimutan gimel. First let me just describe the
case. משוכה והיא תלויה meshucha ve-hi tluyah is we were assuming that
משוכה meshucha meant out here and תלויה tluyah meant right away from
the edges of the מבוי mavoi in here. He is saying no.
משוכה meshucha is away from the edges of the מבוי mavoi in
here. תלויה tluyah means that not only is it not touching the
edges, it's also higher. It's not flat against the top. Okay, it's
higher. So what we have to do is we have to conceptually
both bring it down so it's touching the top of the wall
and extend it, extend it so it's touching the walls on the
side and lower it so it's touching the walls on the top.
Okay, so now we might want to say you can't do that
in two directions, לבוד, lavud, even if it's three, you can't both
go down and connect to the side, right? You're sort of drawing
an imaginary connection to two things. I'll give you an example by
the way in a סוכה, sukkah, right,
we have an idea saying that you can extend a wall if
it's ten טפחים tefachim you can extend a wall up. Okay. We
also have an idea, here's your סכך sechach of your סוכה. sukkah.
Here's your wall. If this ends within three טפחים tefachim of the
wall, right, then it's like the סכך sechach is connected to the
edge of your סוכה. sukkah. Very often you have that. The סכך
sechach doesn't reach all the way at the edge, right, but it's
within nine within nine inches or so, three טפחים tefachim you're okay.
That's okay, right? Let's say though your wall did not go all
the way up to your סכך. sechach. Your wall was only ten
טפחים. tefachim. So normally if your wall is ten טפחים tefachim we
say it's okay, you imagine it extends up. Yeah, everybody with me?
If you have a wall ten טפחים, tefachim, but let's say you
go ahead and you extend your wall up and it's still not
touching the סכך. sechach. Can you have the סכך sechach connected to
an
imaginary wall? דופן עקומה dofen akumah though. It's not דופן, dofen, it's
גוד אסיק gud asik and לבוד, lavud, but you some
say you can't. You can only do לבוד lavud to something physical.
You can't do לבוד lavud to an imaginary extended wall. So here,
some say דופן עקומה dofen akumah though. It's not דופן, dofen, it's
גוד אסיק gud asik and לבוד, lavud, but you some say you
can't. You can only do
what? דופן עקומה? dofen akumah? What do you mean? Because of course
it stays up, because you've got these two walls here that the
סכך sechach is resting on, but on your third side it only
you have beams up here that it's resting on. But on your
third side you only have let's, you know, like material that only
goes so high. So you have to imagine this material goes all
the way up. סוכה sukkah is not on. No, the סכך sechach
is on the crossbeams. Okay. That's a real issue by a סוכה,
sukkah, that you can only do לבוד lavud to something physical. You
can't where there's opinions you can't do it to something imaginary. So
similarly here, this is the issue. You've got here the edges of
your מבוי mavoi and your מבוי mavoi goes off that way. And
you've got here your קורה korah and your קורה korah is doesn't
go all the way to the edges and isn't touching and isn't
touching the base. So can you go לבוד lavud here and then
לבוד lavud here? But when you're you know when you're doing but
you're not doing לבוד lavud to anything physical, you're doing it to
something imaginary. You're imaginarily extending this down and then and then connecting
it to this wall. You're not connecting something physical with לבוד, lavud,
you're connecting the imaginary lowering with לבוד. lavud. That's the question, right?
Can you do it in those two directions? And that's why he
says basically no. If it was three here and three here, that
alone would not be enough. In order to say that this beam
is connected to the wall, there has to be three here because
if there's three here, you can do לבוד lavud straight. from this
physical wall to this physical wall but you can't do לבוד lavud
with an imaginary extension to a physical wall. Is that clear what
he's saying? Yeah. Okay. That would explain the opinion of סוכה sukkah
then? Right, exactly. So that's what he says. So שנעץ she-notz let's
read it. שתי יתדות shetei yetedot you see a little picture in
רש״י Rashi how it's higher and not going to the end. שנעץ
שתי יתדות she-notz shetei yetedot
you have two pegs עקומות akumot at an angle על שתי כותלי
מבוי al shetei kotlei mavoi from the two walls of the מבוי.
mavoi. They're sort of pointed up and they're removed from the edges
of the wall of מבוי. mavoi. שאין בגובהן ג׳ she-ein begovahan gimel
within three from the top of the מבוי mavoi but more significantly
ואין בעקמומיתן ג׳ ve-ein be-akmumitan gimel the
diagonal from the edge of the beam to the wall is less
than three. So מהו דתימא או לבוד אמרינן mah de-teima o lavud
amrinan I would say you could either go down and לבוד lavud
either sort of connect within three horizontally או חבוד אמרינן o chavud
amrinan or throw down meaning imaginarily lower it within three. But לבוד
וחבוד לא אמרינן lavud ve-chavud lo amrinan
you can't both imaginarily lower it and then extend it קא משמע
לן kamashma lan that you can. But really in a certain way
you can't because if this was not three you would not be
allowed to both go down and then extend the imaginary lowering. Right?
You can only extend from physical to physical essentially. Yeah are you
with me? So only because this is three can you connect this
physical edge of the קורה korah to this corner of the מבוי.
mavoi. But if this were three and that were three then you
could not because then you would only be able to connect the
imaginary lowering with the edge and that wouldn't be good. So you
can both lower it and move it because you can go straight
through by the diagonal. The diagonal within three. Yes. The bottom line:
do we differentiate between סוכה sukkah and this case? Well that is
a good question and that points us to a תוספות Tosfos because
תוספות Tosfos says why does the גמרא Gemara think it has to
be directly touching the wall? Like
by a סוכה sukkah I just got through telling you if the
wall's ten טפחים tefachim and the סכך schach is very high you
can imaginarily extend the wall up. Why here does the גמרא Gemara
think that it has to be within three טפחים tefachim of the
wall and it has to be literally physically touching the wall? So
take a look at תוספות Tosfos and here it's interesting in ways
in which you know מבוי mavoi is different than סוכה. sukkah. שאין
בגובהן ג׳ she-ein begovahan sheloshah תוספות Tosfos says ואם תאמר ve-im tomar
ואמר בסוף פרק הישן ve-amar be-sof perek hayashen in סוכה sukkah we
said הישן hayashan I'm sorry הישן hayashen thank you הישן hayashen דכי
יש ברחבו טפח אמרי חבוד רמי de-chi yesh berachvo tefach amri chavud
rami חבוד ורמי chavud u-rami אפילו ביתר מג׳ afilu beyeter migimel that
you can imaginarily throw down the סכך schach even more than three
וקורה דרחבו טפח נימא נמי חבוד רמי אפילו גובה ביתר מג׳ ve-kora
de-rachvo tefach neima nami chavud rami afilu govah beyeter migimel בלאו הכי
קשיא be-lav hachi kashya אמאי לא שריא אפילו ביתר מג׳ כיון דקורה
תוך עשרים. amai lo sharya afilu beyeter migimel keivan de-kora toch esrim.
Anyway תוספות Tosfos basically the upshot of it is whoever said you
needed it to be within three of the top why do you
have to assume that the קורה's korah touching the top of the
wall? ויש לומר דהכא בעינן קורה אגבי מבוי ve-yesh lomar de-hacha beinun
korah agabbai mavoi like we said before yes one of the requirements
of a קורה korah is literally it's touching the top of the
מבוי mavoi וביותר מג׳ לא הוי היכר u-beyeter migimel lo havei hecker
and he tries to explain it based on the idea of היכר.
hecker. If it's more than three it's not a היכר. hecker. תדע
דהמשוכה מבחוץ אפילו פחות מג׳ לא אמרינן לבוד. teda de-hamshucha mibachutz afilu
pachot migimel lo amrinan lavud. The very fact that we said on
the outside it doesn't work even though if you could say לבוד.
lavud. So תוספות Tosfos is saying you cannot assume what's true by
סוכה sukkah is true by the מבוי. mavoi. Each one has its
criteria. By סוכה sukkah it could be very distant the סכך schach
from the wall. Here there are very specific criteria of the קורה
korah and one is that it has to be touching the top
of the wall. It cannot be higher even though by סכך schach
that's allowed. The wall doesn't have to reach the סכך. schach. Here
it has to be touching or within three and not only that
it cannot even be off to the side at all even within
three. It has to literally be on top. Okay so it's not
the same by סוכה sukkah and here. And here we're saying how
about this case seems to say that if it is extended away
it's okay? No it's not talking about that. It's talking that it
is higher or that it's not reaching the edges but not that
it's extended in front of the מבוי. mavoi. And the חידוש chiddush
of this one is that you can say both lower it and
move it to the side but only if even at the angle
it's within three טפחים. tefachim. All right now the גמרא Gemara continues.
תני רב זכאי קמיה דרבי יוחנן. tani Rav Zakkai kammai de-Rabbi Yochanan.
רב זכאי Rav Zakkai taught in front of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
בין הלחיים ותחת הקורה נידון ככרמלית. bein hachayayim ve-tachas hakorah nidun ke-karmelis.
This is another way of saying whether you're allowed to carry underneath
the beam or opposite the לחי lechi and here he's saying you're
not allowed to carry opposite it. The way he phrases it is
that it has a status of a כרמלית karmelis not a status
of a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So if you're under the beam
or opposite the לחי lechi that's not within the הכשר hechsher of
the מבוי mavoi that's not within the legitimate space of the מבוי
mavoi you're not allowed to carry there. So if you're not allowed
to carry there effectively it has a status of a כרמלית karmelis
not a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So that's what he said in
front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר ליה. amar lei. רב יוחנן
Reb Yochanan says to him, פוק תני לברא, puk tani levra, go
teach it to the outside, which is not a compliment. Means don't
teach it around here, okay, which is that this is not a
legitimate ברייתא. braisa. Nope, that's not true, it does not have the
status of a כרמלית, karmelis, presumably רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan felt you
can use underneath the beam and opposite the לחי. lechi. That's exactly
what a ברייתא braisa is. ברייתא Braisa is outside, yeah, but here
it means right, don't teach that in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, מסתברא מילתא דרב יוחנן, Mistavra
miltha d'Reb Yochanan, תחת הקורה. tachas hakorah. I agree with רב יוחנן
Reb Yochanan underneath the beam, that that's okay to use, like we've
been saying, their opinions you can use underneath the beam. אבל בין
לחיים, Aval bein lechayayim, but opposite the לחי, lechi, אסור, assur, like
the גמרא Gemara said before, for whatever reason, not explicated in the
גמרא, Gemara, I gave you תוספות's Tosafos's reason, but he says opposite
the לחי, lechi, I don't agree, that's going to be forbidden. ורבא
אמר, V'Rava amar, רבא Rava says, בין לחיים נמי מותר. bein lechayayim
nami mutar. No, opposite the לחי lechi is also
מותר, mutar, at least it's a consistent position, opposite the לחי lechi
is like under the קורה. korah. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now we're
going to get to that discussion, since we've been discussing the קורה
korah and now we get to the discussion of the לחי. lechi.
So says רבא, Rava, מנא אמינא לה, Mena amina lah, where do
I say, what's my basis for saying that opposite the לחי lechi
is permissible? You ask nowadays when you say you can go actually
right up to the edge of the quote unquote עירוב. eiruv. Yeah,
that would be a good question, except our עירוב eiruv is צורת
הפתח, tzurah hapesach, so you have to ask the same issue as
by a צורת הפתח. tzurah hapesach. צורת הפתח Tzurah hapesach has both
components. So we'll have to... no, it could make it better. So
we'll see about that when we deal with the צורת הפתח. tzurah
hapesach. Okay, מנא אמינא
לה, Mena amina lah, where do I get this idea that opposite
the לחי lechi is okay? דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רב יוחנן,
D'ki atha Rav Dimi amar Reb Yochanan, because when רב דימי Rav
Dimi comes he says in the name of רב יוחנן. Reb Yochanan.
Okay, now of course this is the same רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan
who said that it was okay. But anyway, when רב דימי Rav
Dimi came he said in the name of רב יוחנן: Reb Yochanan:
מקום שאין בו ארבעה על ארבעה מותר לבני רשות הרבים ולבני רשות
היחיד לכתף עליו. Makom she'ein bo arba'ah al arba'ah mutar l'vnei reshus
harabbim ul'vnei reshus hayachid l'katef alav. You might remember this from שבת,
Shabbos, that if you have a beam, let's say a post outside
in the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and it is less than four
by four טפחים, tfachim, think about let's say you have a
mailbox, okay, it's less than ten טפחים tfachim high, it's less than
four by four טפחים tfachim wide, that is considered to be a
מקום פטור, makom p'tur, a sort of no-man's land. Because it's less
than four טפחים, tfachim, it's not significant enough to be considered a
place by itself, and therefore you can even put stuff from a
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim onto it, or you can take stuff from
it and bring it into a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, or bring
it to a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So מותר לבני רשות הרבים
ולבני רשות היחיד לכתף עליו, mutar l'vnei reshus harabbim ul'vnei reshus hayachid
l'katef alav, people
both from the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and from the רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid can put stuff onto this mailbox. ובלבד, U'vilvad,
as long as שלא יחליפו, shelo yachlifu, a guy can't put something
from the mailbox from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim to the mailbox and
then a guy from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid takes something from the
mailbox into the רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, because then you're using it
as a way of getting from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim to רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. But besides that, fundamentally, it is considered a free
zone, neither רשות הרבים reshus harabbim nor רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, not
forbidden on either. Now, what does that have to do with this?
So he's assuming that the space opposite the לחי lechi is less
than four טפחים. tfachim. So he says, look, even if you consider
it to be not part of the רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, not
part of the מבוי, mavoi, okay, it's a space less than four
טפחים tfachim that's not part of the מבוי, mavoi, so let it
be a מקום פטור. makom p'tur. So if it's a מקום פטור,
makom p'tur, you can use it, what's the problem? Okay, so it's
an interesting argument, not because it's part of the מבוי, mavoi, but
because it's מקום פטור. makom p'tur. To which אביי Abaye has a
good
answer. So אביי Abaye would say back to you, התם בגבוה ג',
Hatham b'gavoha gimmel, that's when it's three טפחים tfachim higher than the
floor of רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but when it's literally on the
ground, it's not a מקום פטור. makom p'tur. מקום פטור Makom p'tur's
like its own space. This is on the ground, so it's either
part of the מבוי mavoi and a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, or
part of the space outside of the מבוי, mavoi, which is a
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or a כרמלית. karmelis. You can't have a
מקום פטור makom p'tur on the ground itself, even if it's a
narrow strip that's less than four. Okay, so רבא Rava tried to
argue it because it was like a מקום פטור makom p'tur and
אביי Abaye said, I'm sorry, if it's on the ground, it's part
of one of the רשויות, reshuyos, it's either part of the רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid or part of the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. All
right, so that's אביי's Abaye's response. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so
אביי Abaye says, מנא אמינא לה, Mena amina lah, where do I
get this idea from that it's a problem opposite the לחי? lechi?
דאמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב, D'amar Rav Chama bar Guria
amar Rav, רב חמא בר גוריא Rav Chama bar Guria said in
the name of רב, Rav, תוך הפתח צריך לחי אחר להתיראו. Toich
hapesach tzarich lechi acher l'hatiro. If you want to use the space
inside of the door, okay, now this is similar to Michael's question
here
about what happens if you actually have a door frame. So you
have a מבוי mavoi that has a door frame, and you want
to use the space within the door frame, let's say you have
a very thick wall and you want to use the space within
the door frame, he says you need a לחי lechi
outside of the door frame to use the space within the door
frame. So that seems to be a pretty good proof, because if
you're within the door frame and you can't, that's like opposite the
לחי. lechi. The door frame has the לחיים lechayayim on the side
and you still need another לחי lechi to use the space in
the door frame. It seems like you cannot use the space opposite
the
לחי. lechi. וכי תימא, u'chi teima, thank you. וכי תימא דאיכא ארבעה
על ארבעה, u'chi teima d'ika arba-ah al arba-ah, maybe that case is
worse, that that case is four by four טפחים, tefachim, the width
of the doorframe. And again, if something is four טפחים tefachim wide,
it's more like its own domain. So there, it's more problematic, meaning
part of רבא's Rava argument that it was okay was that it
was like a מקום פטור. makom p'tur. If it's a small space,
it's secondary and ancillary to the מבוי. mavoi. Once it's four טפחים,
tefachim, it has its own significant space, maybe it has its own
independent identity, and maybe that's what makes it a problem to carry
in, because it's no longer ancillary to the מבוי. mavoi. So let's
say you try to tell me, no no no, that case is
a very thick doorframe, a very wide doorframe, and that's why it's
a problem, because it's its own space. You can't say that. דאמר
רב חנין בר רבא אמר רב, d'amar Rav Chanin bar Rava amar
Rav, תוך הפתח, toch hapesach, inside the doorframe, אף על פי שאין
בו ארבעה על ארבעה, af al pi she'ein bo arba-ah al arba-ah,
even if it's not four by four טפחים tefachim wide, צריך לחי
אחר להתירו, tzarich lechi acher l'hatiro, you need another לחי. lechi. So
look, that seems to be a pretty good proof. Within the doorframe,
even if it's a thin strip, you need another לחי, lechi, even
though that's opposite the own frame of the door, the own לחיים
lechis of the door. So you see you cannot use the space
opposite the לחי. lechi. So how do you answer that? ורבא, v'Rava,
רבא Rava will say back to you, התם דפתוח לכרמלית, hasam d'patuach
l'karmelis, that's where the מבוי mavoi and the doorframe opens up into
a
כרמלית, karmelis, like not a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, a side street
or a yard. אבל לרשות הרבים, aval l'reshus harabim, but—so the גמרא
Gemara then responds. So when do I say that you can't, that
you can use the space opposite the לחי, lechi, when it opens
up into a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So the גמרא Gemara is
shocked. גמרא Gemara says,
אבל לרשות הרבים מאי? aval l'reshus harabim mai? Wait, what do you
want to say? If it opens into a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
what's the story? שרי, shari, you can use the space opposite the
לחי? lechi? So יתיבא בארעא ודיורא בשמי שמיא? yativa b'ara v'diyura b'shmei
shamaya? Is the citizen on the ground and the sort of, you
know, the foreigner, you know, the convert up in the heaven? So
meaning it's the opposite, it's crazy that it's better if it opens
into a רשות הרבים reshus harabim than opens into a כרמלית. karmelis.
Opening into a כרמלית karmelis is a less problematic domain. Why should
it be better if it opens into a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
which is a more problematic domain? So the גמרא Gemara says, אין,
in, yes, it is better if it opens into a רשות הרבים
reshus harabim to allow you to carry in that space. Why? And
I mean and it is worse if it opens into a כרמלית.
karmelis. Why? מצא מין את מינו וניעור, matza min es mino v'ne-or,
a one kind found its like and it woke up. A good,
you know, basically this is borrowed language from כשרות, kashrus, which is,
let's say, you know, let's say you dropped a little, I don't
know, drop of חזיר chazir into your stew and it's less than
one-sixtieth, so it's בטל. battel. But then you drop another drop of
חזיר chazir into your stew and now combined it's more than a
sixtieth and can be tasted. So we don't say, oh well that's
also בטל. battel. We say the two combined and now you're able
to taste the חזיר, chazir, it's a problem, which is called מצא
מין את מינו, matza min es mino, one kind found its like
kind, this drop of חזיר chazir discovered the other drop of חזיר
chazir that was dispersed within the stew and it woke it up.
So now you have a, now it can be tasted. It's a
good phrase to use like, you know, if you're sitting in a
class, you know, I gave you this, like, you know, so there
are kids that, you know, if they sit next to each other,
when they're separate they're quiet, but you sit them next to each
other and all of a sudden they start making trouble, it's like
מצא מין את מינו וניעור. matza min es mino v'ne-or. So here's
what the גמרא Gemara says is the same in this case. It
says, you know, the whole idea of this space within the opposite
the doorframe, opposite the beam of the the post of the מבוי,
mavoi, it's in a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, it's between the walls,
but it's in this very gray zone in the walls, it's right
at the edge at the cusp and it's right in the space
not where the where the where the where the post is not
in front of it but it's off to the side. So what's
the story with this gray zone? So it says if you've got
a כרמלית karmelis right outside, then we can say that this gray
zone becomes ancillary not to the מבוי mavoi but becomes ancillary to
the כרמלית. karmelis. It's like an extension of the כרמלית. karmelis. If
you have a major street outside, if it opens right in the
middle of Broadway, you're not going to say this little strip that's
between the walls of a מבוי mavoi is part of Broadway. Okay?
It makes it more of a contrast and therefore it makes it
still connected to the מבוי. mavoi. But if there's like like a,
you know, a sidewalk there, then you can say, okay, that's a
כרמלית karmelis and this also isn't exactly a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
so it's ancillary to the כרמלית. karmelis. So yes, it actually is
worse and it becomes connected to the כרמלית karmelis when it's open
to a כרמלית. karmelis. But if it's open to a רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim, it remains considered by contrast not part of the רשות
הרבים reshus harabim so it remains okay. Yes, has there been a
reason given that I missed why we're treating the לחי. lechi. Well,
if you came after the first five minutes then yes, I mentioned
that תוספות Tosafos says, the גמרא Gemara has not said why,
תוספות Tosafos says since a לחי lechi can be super thin then
we have to be more careful to allow you to use the
space between it, so we might just categorically say you can't use
the space opposite it because it could be so thin and then
it would easily lead to you sort of stepping over that space.
But a לחי lechi can be even thinner. A לחי lechi can
be infinitesimally thin.
All right, I don't know. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר ליה רב הונא, Amar lei Rav Huna, so that's
רבא's Rava defense. Yes, there are times it's a problem when it
opens into a כרמלית. carmelis. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
לרבא. Amar lei Rav Huna b'rei deRav Yehoshua leRava. So רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna b'rei deRav Yehoshua said to רבא, Rava,
את לא תסברה דבין לחיים אסור? At lo tisbera de'vein lachayayim asur?
Would you not agree? How could you not hold that the space
opposite the לחי lechi is forbidden? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, again we
have a statement in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
part of this whole discussion was within the position of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, מבוי שריצפו בלחיים. mavoi sheritzfo belachayayim. If you have a
מבוי mavoi which you basically
like sort of like tiled with לחיים, lachayayim, meaning there's a very
nice picture there in the גמרא. Gemara. Not only did you have
a לחי lechi at the opening, you put consecutive לחיים lachayayim with
gaps between them. Now the gaps, those are like poles? No, those
are לחיים. lachayayim. They're just poles. What do you mean? You don't
have that picture in the גמרא Gemara itself? In the גמרא, Gemara,
in the גמרא, Gemara, you don't have a picture in the גמרא?
Gemara? Here's the wall of your מבוי. mavoi. You put not only
a לחי lechi here, you put a לחי lechi here and a
לחי lechi here and a לחי lechi here and a לחי lechi
here and a לחי lechi here all the way into the inside
of the מבוי. mavoi. Now, פחות פחות מארבע, pachus pachus me'arba, the
space between those לחיים lachayayim is less than ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah tefachim,
more than three but less than four. מנו למחלוקת רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל ורבנן. Manu lemachlokes Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel veRabbanan. It's the debate
of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and the רבנן
Rabbanan because רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you
say לבוד lavud less than four, so it's all like they're all
connected. And the רבנן Rabbanan say you need to be less than
three, and since those are more than three, they're not connected. And
who cares if you say that they're all connected or not connected?
So the גמרא Gemara is going to figure it out. Well, let's
take a look. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say
here's what must be what it means. לרבן שמעון בן גמליאל דאמר
אמרינן לבוד, LeRabban Shimon ben Gamliel de'amar amrinan lavud, according to רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel you say לבוד lavud up
to four. So משתמש עד חודא פנימי, mishtamesh ad chuda pnima'i, if
it's all one big thick לחי, lechi, right, if you make it
all one big thick לחי, lechi, then you can only use up
to the innermost לחי. lechi. Okay, this meaning if you assume you
can't use the space between the you know opposite the לחי, lechi,
right? So if you have all of these tiny little לחיים lachayayim
and you make it one big thick לחי, lechi, so if the
לחי lechi now goes because you've combined them, you know, to be
like this deep לחי lechi all the way in, so you can
only use the מבוי mavoi up to the innermost לחי, lechi, assuming
you can't use the space between the you know opposite the לחי.
lechi. So if you say לבוד משתמש עד חודא פנימי של לחי.
lavud mishtamesh ad chuda pnima'i shel lechi. So של לחי הפנימי, shel
lechi hapnima'i, you can only go up to the inner face of
the inner
לחי. lechi. ולרבנן דאמרי לא אמרינן לבוד, Ulerabbanan de'amri lo amrinan lavud,
the רבנן Rabbanan say you would not say לבוד lavud because it's
more than
three, so משתמש עד חודא פנימי של חיצון. mishtamesh ad chuda pnima'i
shel chitzon. You can go up to the inner face of the
outermost לחי lechi because only one thing is a לחי, lechi, the
thing at the very end. But the only way that saying that
debate makes sense is if you assume you cannot use the space
opposite the
לחי. lechi. אבל בין לחיים דכולי עלמא אסור, Aval bein lachayayim dechulei
alma asur, everybody would say it's forbidden. Because if you can use
the space opposite the לחי, lechi, who cares if you say לבוד
lavud or not? You could always use the space. So it's only
an interesting debate, it only makes sense to see it's an issue
assuming that you cannot use the space opposite the לחי. lechi. So
again, we have a proof that the space opposite the לחי lechi
is no good. ורבא, VeRava, רבא Rava would say to you, okay,
it's true in that case the space opposite the לחי lechi is
no good. Why? התם נמי דפתוח לכרמלית, Hasam nami defatuach lecarmelis, because
it opens up into a כרמלית carmelis and there I admit it's
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara goes through what it just said
a minute ago. אבל רשות הרבים מאי? Aval reshus harabim mai? What
would you say? But if it opens to a רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, then what's the story? שרי? Shari? You could use the space
between the לחי lechi opposite the
לחי? lechi? אציבא בארעא וגיוורא בשמיא? Atziva b'ara v'giyora bishmaya? Is the
citizen on the ground and the foreigner on top? אין מטמנית מיניה
וביה נהור? In, matmanis minei u'vei nehor? Yes, when it finds its
like kind, it wakes up. So when an outside is a כרמלית,
carmelis, makes it worse. So that's always an easy answer that רבא
Rava has to try to disprove him is that yes, it's a
problem when outside is a כרמלית. carmelis. So as you see, this
is interesting indication why when we began the גמרא Gemara today, the
גמרא Gemara said underneath the קורה korah could be debated, but opposite
the לחי, lechi, everybody says it's a problem because there's a lot
of evidence, as we're quoting now, that opposite a לחי lechi is
a problem. So רבא Rava is the one lone voice that says
opposite the לחי lechi is okay, and he has to deal with
all this evidence by saying, but I will concede it when the
when it opens into a כרמלית. carmelis. But when it opens into
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, there I will continue to say that
it's okay opposite the לחי. lechi. One minute, רב אשי Rav Ashi
has another, turn the page, another way of reading this issue of
consecutive לחיים lachayayim to explain what's going on without... being a proof
against
רבא. Rava. רב אשי אמר כגון שרצפו בלחיים פחות פחות מארבעה במשך
ארבע אמות. Rav Ashi amar kagon sheritzvo belachayayin pachos pachos me'arba bemeshech
arba amos. Here's what it means: the issue there was not because
you say לבוד, lovud, you can't use the space between it, and
you use that as a proof against רבא. Rava. The issue was
you had a lot of these consecutive לחי lechi all the way
that it extended ארבע אמות four amot deep into the מבוי. mavoi.
Now why is that relevant? Because you will remember that we say
the minimum size of a מבוי mavoi is ארבע אמות. four amos.
So if you had turned all these individual לחיים lechis into a
consecutive like thing based on לבוד, lovud, like it's a whole wall,
then basically what you've done is you've created a מבוי mavoi within
your מבוי, mavoi, right? If you had here your space and you
had all of these לחי, lechi, right? So what difference does it
make if you said לבוד? lovud? So the first assumption we're making
is that if you said לבוד, lovud, it becomes a big thick
לחי lechi and then you can't use this space. And that proves
against רבא Rava that you can't use the space opposite the לחי.
lechi. Now we're saying, no, if you say לבוד lovud and this
is ארבע אמות, four amot, so basically you've got here a space
that is ארבע אמות four amot that has its own little wall,
that's right, or at least even on one side, right? It's got
its own special wall, different than the wall of that space. So
this becomes its own מבוי, mavoi, okay? Even though it's not really
different, it just has an additional, you know, wall alongside, but it
becomes its own מבוי. mavoi. If this becomes its own מבוי, mavoi,
then it needs its own לחי. lechi. And this becomes a wall
of the מבוי, mavoi, it needs its own לחי. lechi. And this
space might be אסור, assur, because it doesn't have a לחי. lechi.
This is just a wall of a מבוי, mavoi, right? And this
might also need its own לחי lechi in order for it to
be permissible. So the problem is not that you can't use the
space opposite the לחי. lechi. The problem is that if it becomes
ארבע אמות, four amot, it stops being a לחי lechi and starts
becoming a wall and defines it as its own מבוי. mavoi. Exactly
my question: how thick can a לחי lechi be in order to
stop? There you go. Okay, so now you go, see, you wait
a little bit and all will be answered. So רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel דאמר אמרינן לבוד, de'amar aminan lovud, if
you say לבוד, lovud, so all those לחי lechi become a wall,
הוי ליה מבוי, havei leh mavoi, it becomes its own מבוי. mavoi.
וצריך לחי אחר להתירו, vetzarich lechi acher lehatiro, now you need a
new לחי lechi because it stops being a לחי, lechi, it becomes
a wall. Okay, we had that before, that if you actually make
the לחי lechi too big, it stops being a לחי lechi and
now you need a לחי. lechi. Okay, וצריך לחי אחר להתירו. vetzarich
lechi acher lehatiro. ורבנן verabbanan דאמרי לא אמרינן לבוד, de'amri lo aminan
lovud, the רבנן Rabbanan say you don't say לבוד, lovud, לא צריך
לחי אחר להתירו, lo tzarich lechi acher lehatiro, you don't need it,
you only have one לחי. lechi. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: now we get to another discussion. So that was the
issue of under the קורה kora and the discussion of opposite the
לחי, lechi, and now we're going to get to another, we're going
to use this to turn to another discussion which we saw yesterday
as well, which is how visible the לחי lechi has to be.
To the people on the inside or the people on the outside?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel ליהוי כנראה מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים. le'havei kenireh mibachutz veshaveh
mibifnim. So the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get it, even if
this became a wall, why do you need a, why do you
need another לחי? lechi? Okay, so again, you had this, you had
all of these, we said לבוד lovud and it became a wall.
So the גמרא Gemara says I don't get why you need another
לחי. lechi. Because the גמרא Gemara assumes that it says this should
be a case where while it's not visible to the people on
the inside, right, to them it just looks like a wall, to
the people on the outside it is visible. Why is it visible?
It's not so clear. רש"י Rashi sort of assumes that if, like,
if this were, here's the bird's eye view, if this was the
wall of the מבוי mavoi and here you were putting these לחי
lechi up, that the first לחי lechi would have extended a little
bit out. So even though for the people in the מבוי mavoi
it looks like it's just part of a wall, people outside you
can actually see something protruding out. And maybe that should be enough
if the לחי lechi is visible to people on the outside even
if not visible to people on the inside. There, I'll show you
a picture that my my גמרא Gemara has, these nice colorful pictures.
This is the way רש"י Rashi assumes it. תוספות Tosfos questions why,
why it necessarily assumes that way. Anyway, by the way, here's this
nice picture about the קורה kora that was suspended, right? So you
see that? Right? This was the one about the קורה kora that
was raised and also off to the side.
Okay, anyway this one is this picture here. You see the, you
see like the row of the לחי lechi going in, the lower
page here? Okay, but רש"י Rashi assumes that the outermost one לחי
lechi also protrudes out a little bit. So he says even if
it's going to be a wall here, but it's a wall that
from the outside perspective is seen to protrude off out of where
it expects the flush face to be. So for example, so the
idea being, right, if this were one wall of the מבוי mavoi
and and this wall you had, you know, you had a piece,
trying to see what it would look like here this way. If
this were the edge of a wall of a מבוי mavoy and
you had this thing here like this, okay, and I'm specifically making
it thinner. So on the inside it does not look like a
לחי. lechi. On the inside it looks like it's just a continuation
of the wall. But on the outside, because it's not the same
thickness, people say, oh look, there's a beam sticking out of that
wall, right, because it's not the same thickness. So that's an example
of visible from the outside and not the inside. So the גמרא
Gemorah assumes that in this description, somehow that would have been the
scenario. So it says, I don't get it, even if you turned
the whole thing into a wall, isn't it still visible from the
outside?
וליחזי, v'lichzei, let me see that again, ליהוי כנראה מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים,
lehavei kenira mibachutz veshaveh mibifnim, let it still be visible from the
outside even though it's flush on the inside. גמרא Gemorah says no,
מידי דהוי טעמא אלא לרבי יוחנן, midi dahavei ta'ama ela l'Rabbi Yochanan,
this whole issue is discussing the position of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
And we know that רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, כי אתא רבין, ki
ata Ravin, and when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, he said in the name of
רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: נראה מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים, nira mibachutz veshaveh mibifnim,
if it's visible on the outside and flush on the inside, אינו
נידון משום לחי, eino nidon mishum lechi, it does not count as
a לחי. lechi. So that ends our discussion because of that and
now we're going to turn to this latter point. So what did
we discuss today so far? Underneath the קורה, kora, can you use
it or not? Debated. It's not really based on, it could go
either way whether קורה kora is היכר heker or קורה kora is
מחיצה, mechitzah, but still the question is היכר heker on the inside
or היכר heker on the outside, מחיצה mechitzah on the inside or
מחיצה mechitzah on the outside. Now this idea, okay, so that's one
issue. How about opposite the לחי? lechi? All of the evidence seems
to say that that's a problem. Why is it different? תוספות Tosafot
say because a לחי lechi could be very thin. But anyway, רבא
Rava says it's not a problem. What does he do with the
evidence? Most of the evidence he says is when it's next to
a כרמלית. karmelit. Then I'll admit that that space opposite the לחי
lechi is problematic, but when it's facing רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, that
space is actually okay. So the space of the לחי lechi is
more potentially problematic than under the קורה. kora. And now we turn
to this last issue about what is the story of a לחי
lechi can be seen from the outside and not the inside. And
to some degree that's similar to the issue I mentioned about whether
the קורה kora has to be a היכר heker for the inside
or is it enough that it's a היכר heker for the outside?
So the same issue can be raised by the לחי. lechi. If
it's visible from the outside not the inside, is that good enough?
And that's now what we're going to turn to and that'll be
the focus for the rest of today. If there is recognition as
something that's more in potential than actuality? I mean, what does he
mean it's such an architecture that you can't really tell it's functioning
as a לחי lechi or קורה? kora? Let's say it's good, right?
So, well that's always the issue, you know, even if it's a
היכר heker we translate היכר heker into certain quantifiable criteria. Okay, and
the question is, is this one of those quantifiable criteria? So let's
take a look. איתמר, itmar, so it was
taught: נראה מבפנים ושווה מבחוץ, nira mibifnim veshaveh mibachutz, if it is
visible on the inside but flush on the outside, okay, that's something,
you know, that you can easily imagine which is sort of the
opposite type of a case that it's like sticking out this way,
right? So if you're walking on the outside you just think the
wall's a little thicker, but if you're here on the inside, right,
you sort of see it's protruding out from the wall, right? So
that's the case where that's an obvious case. So in that case
נידון משום לחי, nidon mishum lechi, clearly that's a לחי, lechi, it's
visible to the people on the inside.
נראה מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים, nira mibachutz veshaveh mibifnim, if it's the opposite,
it's like this, right? The scenario I gave you before, so on
the inside it looks flush, but on the outside you see that
it's protruding. So that's an issue. Is the visibility to the people
on the outside sufficient? רבי חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי, Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi
Shimon beribi, so it's a debate of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and
רבי שמעון ברבי, Rabbi Shimon beribi, both of them sort of תלמידים
talmidim of רבי, Rebbi, one רבי's Rebbi son. חד אמר נידון משום
לחי, chad amar nidon mishum lechi, one says it counts as a
לחי, lechi, it's enough that it's visible on the outside. וחד אמר
אינו נידון משום לחי, v'chad amar eino nidon mishum lechi, it doesn't
count. תסתיים, tistayaim, says the גמרא, Gemorah, let's conclude דרבי חייא הוא
דאמר נידון משום לחי, d'Rabbi Chiya hu d'amar nidon mishum lechi, רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya is the one that says it is good. Why
should we conclude that? דתני רבי חייא d'tani Rabbi Chiya because רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya taught the following
ברייתא: braita: כותל שצידו אחד כנוס מחבירו, kotel shetzido echad kanus mechaveiro,
exactly as I've been describing, except sort of maybe this is Michael's
point, that it's not that you even stuck a post, but actually
the way you configured the wall was that the wall itself was
like, you know, one, like sort of protruded, like the edge of
the wall looked like this, okay? That was the way the edge
of the wall looked. All right, you didn't even make a post,
all right? So it was, this is the inside of the מבוי,
mavoy, right? So this type of a thing, it's נראה מבפנים, nira
mibifnim, it's as if you had made a post here, but from
the outside it just looks like the wall. Okay? You see that
if that's your configuration of the wall? It could be visible on
the inside and not on the outside. If it's the other way,
it could be visible on the outside but not the inside. What
would be that scenario? Let me see that. You're facing the other
way. You're facing this way.
Like that? No. You would be facing, how would it be visible
on the outside and not the inside? Like
that, exactly on the outside and then it just moves in. Okay,
that's visible on the that's visible on the outside and not on
the inside. Okay, so that's what you have is your configuration of
your wall.
So that's a ברייתא. Baraitha. So תניא דבי רבי חייא: Tanya d'vei
Rabbi Hiyya: כותל שצדו אחד כנוס מחברו. Kotel shetzido echad kanus michavero.
You have a wall that one side is a little bit indented.
בין שנראה מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים, Bein shenireh mibachutz veshaveh mipanim, whether it's
in such a way that the protrusion is visible on the outside
and flush on the inside; בין שנראה מבפנים ושווה מבחוץ, bein shenireh
mipanim veshaveh mibachutz, it's visible on the inside and flush on the
outside, נידון משום לחי. nidon mishum lechi. It's good. So here it's
an explicit teaching that if it's visible on even if it's only
visible on the outside, it's okay. And it's רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya
teaches this ברייתא. Baraitha. So you see that's רבי חייא's Rabbi Hiyya
position. So the גמרא Gemara says תסתיים. tista'ye. Yeah, that's a good
proof that רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya holds that that's okay. So the
גמרא Gemara now says I don't get it. רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
remember we said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it's no good. מי
לא שמיע ליה הא? Mi lo shmeia lei ha? He must have
heard this ברייתא Baraitha and nevertheless he rejected it. אלא שמיע ליה
ולא סבר לה. Ehlah shmeia lei vilo savar lah. It must be
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan heard this ברייתא Baraitha that that was good
and he rejected it. So if that's true, let's say the same
about רבי חייא. Rabbi Hiyya. רבי חייא נמי, Rabbi Hiyya nami, even
though רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya taught the ברייתא, Baraitha, just because he
taught it doesn't mean he holds by it. Let's say לא סבר
לה. lo savar lah. So let's say maybe he doesn't hold of
the ברייתא. Baraitha. Maybe you can't prove רבי חייא's Rabbi Hiyya position
even though he taught it. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says:
היי מאי? Hay mai? What are you talking about? בשלמא רבי יוחנן
לא סבר לה. Bishlamah Rabbi Yochanan lo savar lah. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan didn't hold of the ברייתא. Baraitha. משום הכי לא תני לה.
Mishum hachi lo tni lah. Therefore he didn't teach it. Okay. אלא
רבי חייא, Ehlah Rabbi Hiyya, but רבי חייא, Rabbi Hiyya, אי איתא
דלא סבר לה, ee itah delo savar lah, if he didn't believe
in this ברייתא, Baraitha, למה ליה למתניה? lamah lei lemitniyah? What's he
doing going around teaching it? Okay. So the fact that רבי חייא
Rabbi Hiyya taught this ברייתא Baraitha shows that he is of the
position that even if it's only visible on the outside, that's sufficient.
אמר רבה בר רב הונא. Amar Rabba bar Rav Huna. So now
רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna said: נראה מבחוץ ושווה
מבפנים נידון משום לחי. Nireh mibachutz veshaveh mipanim nidon mishum lechi. He
is siding with this רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya position, even if it's
only seen on the outside and flush on the inside, it's still
good. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: ומסייעינן אשמעתא. Umisayinan ashemaita. Now we ask
to this idea that it would be good from the following משנה.
Mishna. Now we actually taught this משנה Mishna last two days. חצר
קטנה שנפרצה לגדולה. Hatzer ktana shenifretza legedola. You see we thought we
were free from that. This again is the case of the remember
we had the
מבוי, mavoi, the מבוי mavoi entering into the חצר. hatzer. So you
have a small חצר hatzer opening into a bigger חצר. hatzer. Okay,
the wall here fell down. Used to be a wall, fell down.
חצר קטנה Hatzer ktana into a חצר גדולה. hatzer gedola. Okay, and
as you remember, the problem is an עירוב. eruv. Because for the
חצר גדולה, hatzer gedola, this is just an opening. Part, you know,
their wall extends in both directions. It's not seen like they necessarily
are feeding into the small one. So the small one doesn't have
to relate to them. They're safe even though they didn't make an
עירוב eruv with the smaller one. But the small one, the whole
wall is open fully into the חצר גדולה. hatzer gedola. They're seen
as part of the חצר גדולה, hatzer gedola, and therefore they're mixed
with people they didn't make an עירוב eruv with and these guys
have a problem of carrying. Okay, we taught that before over the
last few days. חצר קטנה שנפרצה לגדולה, Hatzer ktana shenifretza legedola, small
חצר hatzer opens into a big one.
גדולה מותרת וקטנה אסורה. Gedola muteret u-ktana asura. The big one is
permissible even though it doesn't it has its own עירוב eruv but
as with the small one, it remains permissible. The small one is
forbidden because its whole wall is open up. מפני שכפתחה של גדולה.
Mipne sheke-pitcha shel gedola. The reason the big one is okay is
this is like an opening for the big one, but it's not
an opening for the small one. It's an entire lack of a
wall. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. One minute. ואי איתא,
Ve-ee itah, if a לחי lechi that's visible on the outside is
sufficient, קטנה נמי תשתרי. ktana nami tishtrei.
It says in order for this to separate itself off from the
big one, it would just need some type of a thing. It
wouldn't need a whole צורת הפתח. tzurat ha-petach. A לחי lechi would
be enough and a לחי's lechi enough to separate it from a
רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, a לחי lechi would be enough to separate
it from the big one. So the גמרא Gemara says it's got
a לחי! lechi! Why does it have a לחי? lechi? This. This
is like a protrusion off from the side. So even though these
people don't see the protrusion, if you're looking in, you see that
something protrudes outside of the wall. So this should count like a
לחי lechi that's visible from the outside and not visible from the
inside. Now you're giving a quizzical look because you're saying it's a
little different if it's like that by itself than if it's just
part of a wall. It's true, but the גמרא Gemara assumes that
that should be sufficient. That's like a לחי, lechi, something that protrudes,
that's visible from the outside and not the inside. So why shouldn't
that work as a לחי lechi to separate itself off?
So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב זירא בנכנסים כותלי קטנה לגדולה.
Amar Rav Zeira benichnasim kotlei ktana legedola. Okay, so it says here's
why. If it were that scenario, it would be okay. Here the
case is that the walls extend in and then it broke. So
this had been the configuration like this and then this wall fell
down and now... Now these walls, there's no לחי, lechi, right? Nothing
protrudes off the side of those walls. And that's why you've got
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולימא לבוד ותישתרי. velima lavud
vetishteri. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but wait. It assumes that,
we'll see why it assumes this in a minute, that this is
not so much bigger. This is only a little bit bigger.
So and maybe it assumes that there's within three טפחים tefachim here
of the side of the wall. So I don't get it, says
the גמרא. Gemara. Let's say לבוד, lavud, consider it attached to the
side of the wall and turn this effectively into a לחי. lechi.
Pretty funny, turning it into a לחי lechi by basis of לבוד.
lavud. But if you consider this wall attached within three טפחים, tefachim,
then that should be again like a protrusion and that should be
a לחי. lechi. So the גמרא Gemara now, how do you know
it's so close to the edge of the wall? וכי תימא דמפליג
טובא, vechi teima demaplig tuva, let's if you say that it's very
distant from the edge, doesn't have to be very distant, just more
than three טפחים. tefachim. That's not true. והתני רב אדא בר אבימי
קמיה דרב חנינא, vehatani Rav Adda Bar Avimi kamei deRav Chanina, we
Rav Adda Bar Avimi explains, gives a ברייתא beraita to explain this
משנה. mishna. And he says, קטנה בעשר גדולה באחת עשרה. ketana be'eser
gedola be'achat esreh. It's even if the small one was only ten
אמות amot and the big one was eleven אמות. amot. What's the
difference between ten אמות amot and eleven אמות? amot? אמה. amah. How
many טפחים tefachim in an אמה? amah?
Six. There's a מחלוקת. machlokes.
Yeah, yeah, but okay, we say six. So with six, if this
is ten and this is eleven, you've got three טפחים tefachim on
each side. Now לבוד lavud is less than three טפחים, tefachim, but
you have the thickness of the wall. So because of the thickness
of the wall, okay, if this is ten and this whole thing
is eleven, this is less than three on each side. So let's
say לבוד lavud and let that function as a לחי. lechi. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבינא במופלג מכותל זה בשניים ומכותל זה
בארבעה. Amar Ravina bemufleg mikotel zeh bishnayim umikotel zeh be'arba'ah. Who told
you it was exactly centered? That's two טפחים tefachim here and four
טפחים tefachim here. So you can't say לבוד lavud here. So the
obvious question is, okay, you can't say לבוד lavud here, but you
can say לבוד lavud here and you only need one לחי. lechi.
So we're still back to the problem: if the visible on the
outside is good, then even invisibly visible, which is pretty funny, even
based on לבוד, lavud, we should consider that to be a לחי
lechi and why is that not good? So the גמרא Gemara says,
ולימא לבוד מרוח אחת ותישתרי. velima lavud meruach achat vetishteri. Let's say
לבוד lavud on one side and let it be allowed. So the
גמרא Gemara says, רבי היא דאמר בעינא שני פסים. Rabbi hee de'amar
beina shenei pasim. It's Rabbi who said that you need two planks,
a plank on either side and not just a plank on one
side. Now that's very unusual. We've always been talking about one לחי.
lechi. But that's about a מבוי. mavoi. A חצר, chatzer, there's an
opinion that you might need something on both sides. So we will
talk about this tomorrow. Okay, stay tuned.